"Phone Home Durham" Exhibit Prints, 2012-2015 and undated RL.11190
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
"Phone Home Durham" exhibit prints
2012-2015 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Rankin, Tom
RL.11190
2 Linear Feet 3 boxes; 85 13x19 inch inkjue prints; 43 manuscript items
Collection comprises 85 13x19 inch photographic prints and other documents related to the exhibit, "Phone Home Durham, 2015." The images were all taken by 50 residents of Durham County, North Carolina, chiefly with mobile phones but also with handheld cameras, and are mostly color digital prints, with a few black-and-white prints. The photographers focused on urban settings, although there are a few rural images taken in Durham County. The images reflect society and customs in 21st century Durham, with subject content including protests relating to race issues, street scenes, graffiti, abandoned houses, local shops and businesses, industrial buildings, and a few landscapes with trees and sunsets. The exhibit prints are accompanied by exhibit guides and other publicity related to the 2015 exhibition, several photographers' statements, and the original exhibit proposal by Duke University professor and photographer Tom Rankin. The exhibit was co-curated by Aaron Canipe, Alexa Dilworth, Jeremy Lange, and Jim Lee. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Collection Overveiw
The collection comprises 85 13x19 inch inkjet prints of photographs, chiefly in color, taken by 50 photographers from Durham County, North Carolina. The images were selected from submissions to the Center for Documentary Studies in response to a call for "images of Durham County [N.C.] taken with mobile phone cameras or other hand held devices." The size of the actual image on the 13x19 print varies and can be as small as 4x6 inches.
The photographers focused on urban settings, although there are a few rural images taken in Durham County. The images reflect society and customs in 21st century Durham, with subject content including protests relating to race issues, street scenes, graffiti, abandoned houses, local shops and businesses, industrial buildings, and a few landscapes with trees and sunsets. Locations include the Durham History Hub, Museum of Life and Science, Duke University, Liberty Cafe, Taqueria Gonzales, Geer Street, Eno River State Park, Ellerbee Creek bridge, Pelican Snoballs, Catsburg Store, the beaver pond off of Avondale Drive, Compare Foods, Durham Central Park, Cocoa Cinnamon coffee shop, Durham County Detention Facility, West Chapel Hill Street bridge, Beyu Cafe, the Durham Bulls ballpark, the 40th Centerfest, El Vaquero Western Wear Shop, 21c Museum Hotel, and the Scrap Exchange.
The exhibit was guest curated by Aaron Canipe, Alexa Dilworth, Jeremy Lange and Jim Lee and displayed in different rotations at the Power Plant Gallery at the American Tobacco Campus from May 29, 2015 to August 22, 2015.
The photographic prints are accompanied by five exhibit guides arranged by dates of exhibition, with thumbnails of each image, the photographer's name, and captions or additional information. Other documents are a flyer explaining request for submissions, a Durham County Library program flyer, and photographers' statements about their images. Also located here is the proposal for the exhibit written by Tom Rankin, documentary photographer and Director of the Master of Fine Arts Program at Duke University.
The following photographers are represented in the collection: D.L. Anderson, Kristina Baker, Daniele Berman, Eric Boven, Michaela Brooks, Aaron Canipe, Mario Chen, Christina Chia, Ira Christmas, Olisa Corcoran, Diane Davis, Wilfred Drath, B.J. Fusaro, Roman Gabriel, Alexa Gerend, Cynthia Gurganus, Izzy (Isaac) Hart, Jim Haverkamp, Warren Hicks, Juliet Jensen, Jim Kellough, Frank Konhaus, Stephanie Leathers, Ryan Mason, Mark Maya, Eleanor Mills, Jesse Moore, John Moses, Callistus Ndemo, Michael Palko, Bill Pope, Courtney Reid-Eaton, Julie Rhodes, Jacqueline Rimmler, Emily Rush, Katherine Scott, Adelle Smith, Amanda Smith, Daniel Smith, Lisa Sorg, Jennifer Stratton, Gina Streaty, Amanda Stricklett, Dawn Surratt, Lynda-Marie Taurasi, Aiyana Torres, Cait Ushpol, Ross Wade, Carin Walsh, and Josh Zaslow.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Organized into two series: Photographs, and Publicity. Prints are arranged alphabetically by photographers' last name.
Historical Note
The idea for the project "Phone Home Durham" came from Tom Rankin, former director of the Center for Documentary Studies, professor of the practice of art and documentary studies, and director of the MFA in Experimental and Documentary Arts at Duke University. Financial support for the exhibit was provided by Museo Digital Fine Art Media.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The "Phone Home Durham" collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2015.
Related Materials
Will Grossman photographs
Rubenstein Library, Duke University
Center for Documentary Studies student projects collection, 1980-2011 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Literacy Through Photography Collection
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library, Duke University
Documentary photography -- North Carolina -- Durham; Documentary photography -- North Carolina -- Durham County; Graffiti -- North Carolina; Industrial buildings -- Durham County (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Buildings, structures, etc. -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Durham (N.C.) -- Race relations; Durham (N.C.) -- Social conditions; Durham (N.C.) -- Social life and customs; Durham County (N.C.) -- Pictorial works; Black-and-white photographs; Color photographs; Digital prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Canipe, Aaron; Dilworth, Alexa; Lange, Jeremy; Lee, Jim
- Photographs, 2012-2015 and undated
  Arrangement
  The photographs are arranged by the photographer's last names, in alphabetical order. The titles derive from those written on the backs of the prints. There are often alternate titles or additional captions found in the gallery guide and exhibit list; these are recorded in the notes accompanying each print.
  - Anderson, D.L.
    - West Point on the Eno, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Moving out, the West End, Durham, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      Scope and Contents
      The alternate title in the gallery guide was "Moving Out, Gattis Street, Durham, 2014."
  - Baker, Kristina
    - The green room, 2015 March 20 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Berman, Daniele
    - Baby ballet at Barriskill, undated, 2 copies (Box 1, Folder 2)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list was "Little girl ballet dancing." There is a duplicate print mislabeled "Hanging Christmas lights on a tower."
    - Luke Jackson playing catcher for South Durham Little League, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list was "Catcher at home plate."
  - Boven, Eric
    - Field as I turn to go home, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Preparing food, 2015 March-April (Box 1, Folder 3)
      The caption in the gallery guide also listed that photo was taken at a farm near the northern county line.
  - Brooks, Michaela
    - Pelican's SnoBalls, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Canipe, Aaron
    - 3/31/2015, 3:31pm, Blackwell St. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Title in gallery guide is listed as "February 25, 2015, 8:09am, Campus Drive."
    - 2/25/2015, 7:08 pm, Ninth St., 2015 February 25; (2 copies (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "2/25/15, 7:08pm Ninth St., Ms. Pacman."
    - Pettigrew St., 2014 October 27 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Tree on Pettigrew St."
  - Chen, Mario
    - Snow attack at the ball park, 2015 February 24 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Footprints in the snow at Diamondview (Durham Bulls park)."
    - Under the bridge off Alston Ave in East Durham, 2015 June 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
      Date of image taken from gallery guide. Black-and-white photograph is of graffiti, including a Bible verse quote next to image of what looks like the face of Jesus Christ.
  - Chia, Christina
    - Game room at the Carmike Wynnsong 15, 2014 September 6 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Christmas, Ira
    - Catsburg country store, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Snow covered Ellerbee Creek Bridge, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Corcoran, Olisa
    - Geer Street sky, 2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Davis, Diane
    - Manshack, 2014 July 12 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Date is listed in gallery guide for May 29 to August 22, 2015.
  - Drath, Wilfred
    - Beyu Cafe, 2015 April 23 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      The alternate title in the gallery guide is "Inside Beyu Cafe."
    - Durham History, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Durham History Hub."
  - Fusaro, B.J.
    - Gas station turned coffee shop / falling snow, 2014 February (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Reincarnation of Liberty warehouse, 2015 January (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Gabriel, Roman
    - A city in transition, storm coming, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Storm with parking lot light." The alternate title in the gallery guide is "City in transition: A storm is coming."
  - Gerend, Alexa
    - Midnight, February 25th, 2011 West Club Blvd, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Tree in snow."
  - Gurganus, Cynthia
    - Penny's Bend Nature Preserve, 2014 April 27 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Hart, Izzy (Isaac)
    - Taken at Durham School of the Arts, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Durham School for the Arts" (young man with camera inside).
    - Taken at Durham School of the Arts, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
      The title in the exhibit list is "Durham School for the Arts" (pointing finger).
  - Havercamp, Jim
    - Growth, 2014 April 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Taken near Watts and Main St. intersection."
    - Sofia on scooter, 2015 May 31 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Taken on 200 block of Dacian Avenue."
  - Hicks, Warren
    - Flying the not so friendly skies, 2014 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Straight up, 2014 August 14 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Jensen, Juliet
    - Backyard bliss (old dog and mower), 2015 September 22 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Dog day."
  - Kellough, Jim
    - Carne, COMPARE @ Avondale, 2015 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Pyramids, COMPARE @ Avondale, 2015 April 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Konhaus, Frank
    - Vinyl, undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Leathers, Stephanie
    - Iredell house, hollow house, 2013 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Tell me where (Liggett Myers), 2015 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Mason, Ryan
    - Abandoned phone booth, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Powerlines and sky, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Taqueria, 2015 April (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Alternate title in exhibit list was "Taqueria Gonzalez."
  - Maya, Mark
    - Graffiti, undated (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Building corner, undated, 2 copies (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Mills, Eleanor
    - Canker worm, 2015 April 28 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Moore, Jesse
    - Englewood Ave, 2015 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Alternate title in exhibit list is "Englewood Ave. (Free Crap sign)."
  - Moses, John Wills, Jr.
    - Parking lot after work 4020 N. Roxboro St., undated (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Ndemo, Callistus
    - Pizza tower, 2015 March 6 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Palko, Michael
    - Durham Museum of Life and Science, 2012 (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Street Art Pettigrew St, 2014 December (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - W. Chapel Hill St. bridge 1, 2015 April (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - W. Chapel Hill St. bridge 2, 2015 April (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Pope, Bill
    - Downtown alley, 2015 February 24 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - I love Durham, 2015 January 18 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      Alternate title in exhibit list is "I love Durham graffiti."
    - Legs, Scrap Exchange, 2012 June 15 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Reid-Eaton, Courtney
    - Wild onions, undated (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rhodes, Julie
    - Corrida, 2013 November 13 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Alternate title in exhibit list is "Duke University Medical Center Library."
  - Rimmler, Jacqueline
    - Beaver pond, 2014 November (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Leaves, 2015 February (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Rush, Emily
    - Storms over Durham, 2014 June 11 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      Alternate title in exhibit list is "Storm over Durham (ATC Lucky Strike tower)."
  - Scott, Katherine
    - Missing super sock, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Sausage gravy and yolk, undated (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Smith, Adelle
    - Flowering trees outside the Fuqua School of Business at Duke University, 2014 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Smith, Amanda
    - Boots at El Vaquero, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Representative John Lewis, 2014 October 4 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Wild swarm of bees in the Durham Arts Council parking lot, undated (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Smith, Daniel
    - Latitude: 36째 10'20.148" N / Longitude: 78째 56' 39.768" W / Rougemont, NC, 2015 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Latitude: 36째 10'20.148" N / Longitude: 78째 56' 39.768" W / Rougemont, NC, 2015 May 24 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Sunset over mother's farm in Rougemont, NC."
  - Sorg, Lisa
    - Durham Central Park, 2013 October 19 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      The alternate title in the gallery guide is "Jazz Band at Durham Central Park." Title on back of print is in error.
    - Uniforms / 21c Museum Hotel, 2015 February 27 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      Title on back of print is in error.
  - Stratton, Jennifer
    - Centerfest, Durham NC, 2014 September 14 (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Free mattress, 2015 April 2 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Free mattress, Farthing St. and Lavender Ave. (Northgate Park, Durham NC)."
    - Hanging flag, 2015 February 3 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Hanging flag, Erwin Rd."
  - Streaty, Gina
    - Guess Road Christ / Guess Road and Carver Street, N. Durham, 2011 May - 2012 August (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Stricklett, Amanda
    - An aged window in the bright southern sun, 2014 September (Box 2, Folder 22)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Rusted peeling paint."
  - Surratt, Dawn
    - Eno River treebank, 2015 February 1 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Eno River State Park."
    - Pink penguins, 2015 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Taurasi, Lynda-Marie
    - At the Pinhook, 2015 January 20 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Torres, Aiyana
    - Simple Mondays, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "House with red door and vines."
    - Wise nights, undated (Box 2, Folder 23)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "Stairs."
  - Ushpol, Caitlin
    - 5/1/15 Durham County Detention Facility, 2015 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      The title in the exhibit list is "May 1 protest #2." The gallery guide caption is "Durham County Detention Facility during a peaceful protest following the death of Freddie Gray in Baltimore. We are united. #blacklivesmatter."
    - Protest, 2015 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      The alternate title in the exhibit list is "May 1 protest." The caption in the gallery guide is "Taken May 1, 2015 outside the Durham County Detention Facility during a peaceful protest. #blacklivesmatter #alllivesmatter #stoppolicebrutality."
  - Wade, Ross
    - Liberty Cafe, Durham, NC, 2014 September-November (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Walsh, Carin
    - 21c Museum Hotel, Stairwell 3, 2015 June 29 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Zaslow, Josh
    - Dog / February 2015 on Club Blvd., 2015 February (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Publicity, 2014-2015; 3 folders
  Folders contain gallery and exhibit guides, fliers, and other publicity, as well as the original proposal written by Tom Rankin, documentary photographer, former director of the Center for Dcoumentary Studies, and Director of the Masters of Fine Arts in Experimental and Documentary Arts Program at Duke University.
  - Publicity materials (Box 3)